ALUN C. STOKES

Hamilton, Ontario (647)-287-2418 — stokea1@mcmaster.ca

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My interests lie at the intersection of computing and mathematics, particularly in number theory. I am currently interested in the theory of dessins d'enfants and the computation of their Belyi maps. In general, I write software for high-performance and distributed computing and have substantial experience in several areas of machine learning.

EDUCATION

Master of Science (Pure Mathematics)

September 2021 - April 2023

McMaster University

Supervisor: Dr Cameron Franc

Bachelor of Integrated Science (Mathematics & Statistics) September 2017 - June 2021

Honours: summa cum laude (10.8/12 GPA) McMaster University

Supervisor: Dr Cameron Franc The Search for Self-Contained Numbers

Turner Fenton Secondary School

September 2013 - June 2017 International Baccalaureate Program 97% Cumulative Average

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Stokes, A. Hum, W., Zaslavsky, J. A Minimal-Input Multilayer Perceptron for Predicting Drug-Drug Interactions Without Knowledge of Drug Structure. **STEM Fellowship Journal.** 6(1):
- [2] †Stokes, A. Automatically Solving Square-Piece Jigsaw Puzzles using Convolutional Neural Networks with Gradient Boosted Decision Trees. The Undergraduate Journal. (12th edition). Accessible at: https://gua.soutron.net/Portal/Default/en-GB/RecordView/Index/61.
- [3] †Stokes, A. The search for self-contained numbers: k-special 3-smooth representations and the Collatz conjecture, 2021, [Online]. Available: https://macsphere.mcmaster.ca/handle/11375/27543

Entries marked with † have **not** been peer-reviewed.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant

May 2021 - August 2021

McMaster University

Dr Cameron Franc

Investigated machine learning strategies to discriminate non-congruence finite-index subgroups of the modular group and strategies to compute Belyi maps corresponding to passports of dessins d'enfants.

Data Scientist

June 2020 - August 2020

Statistics Canada

Consumer Prices Division

Developed NLP methods for hierarchical data structure mapping to aid in calculating the consumer price index.

Research Assistant

May 2020 - July 2020 Dr George Dragomir, Dr Andy Nicas

McMaster University

Building on work by Dragomir and Nicas, we investigated how quasi-hyperbolicity could be exploited to reduce roughness and distortion in quasi-isometric graph embeddings.

Research Assistant

May 2019 - May 2020

McMaster University

Dr Ned Nedialkov

Developed convolutional neural networks to segment photoacoustic breast images for a group from Western University developing a hand-held *in-situ* scanner.

Math & Computer Science Tutor

December 2013 - Present

Private

Worked one-on-one with each of two students to develop skills in math and computer programming.

TALKS AND SEMINARS

[†]Algebra and Algebraic Geometry Seminar

November 2021

McMaster University

An Introduction to Belyi Maps

Gave a 30-minute presentation on dessins d'enfants, their relevance, and pertinent computational techniques used in my research open to McMaster's math faculty and graduate students.

Synopsis 2021 April 2021

McMaster University

k-special 3-smooth Representations and the Collatz Conjecture

A 15-minute expository talk on a formulation of the Collatz conjecture by a family of Diophantine equations and a conjecturally sparse set of numbers that are 'almost' solutions.

CANDEV January 2020

Government of Canada

Using Transformer-based Embeddings to Identify Course Redundancies

Gave a short talk on our use of transfer-learning with a transformer model to cluster courses offered by the Canadian School of Public Service and identify redundancies in course offerings.

Undergraduate Big Data Competition

July 2019

STEM Fellowship

Predicting Drug-Drug Interactions Without Knowledge of Drug Structure

This was a talk given with coauthors on our method of using machine learning to predict *in-vivo* drug-drug interactions using only analytical chemical properties. This was held at York University.

Synopsis 2019 April 2019

McMaster University

Prime Distribution by Linear Flow on the Torus

A 15 minute expository talk on the primary findings of a 4-month project investigating prime distributions over non-intersecting curves on closed surfaces.

Entries marked with † are invited talks.

TEACHING ASSISTANTSHIPS

McMaster University

January 2022 - April 2022

Graduate Topics in Risk Management

MFM 763

Introductory Number Theory

MATH 3H03

McMaster University

September 2021 - December 2021

Numerical Linear Algebra Linear Algebra I MATH 3NA3 MATH 1B03

McMaster University

January 2021 - April 2021

Introduction to Discrete Mathematics

CS 1DM3

OTHER PROJECTS

Global Undergraduate Awards

September 2021

Dr Ned Nedialkov

Fully Automated Jigsaw Puzzle Solving by Hybrid ML

Won first place in North America for a paper on hybrid machine learning techniques to solve squarepiece jigsaws; state-of-the-art matching accuracy was reported.

National Big Data Competition

June 2020

Dr Yasaman Amannejad

Medication Recommendation by Matrix Factorization

Devised a matrix factorization-based recommender system to predict effective drugs for treating several mental illnesses, given a patient's history with other drugs.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages[†] Python, Julia, Java, MATLAB, C/C++, CUDA, JavaScript,

SQL, PHP, Mathematica

Major Libraries SageMath, Pytorch, HomotopyContinuation.jl

Software & Tools LATEX, Git, MySQL

Operating Systems[†] GNU/Linux (Ubuntu, primarily), MacOS, Windows

GRANTS AND AWARDS

Ontario Graduate Scholarship

May 2022 - April 2023

\$15000

NSERC USRA May 2021 - August 2021

\$8120

Dean's Honour List September 2017 - April 2021

Awarded all 4 years of undergraduate dregree

Global Undergraduate Awards September 2020

1st place for computer science in North America

McMaster Stewart Award May 2020

\$3750

CANDEV Data Challenge January 2020

 1^{st} place

STEM Fellowship Big Data Competition

July 2019

\$3000

McMaster President's Award September 2017

\$2500

[†]Listed in order of proficiency